<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Adam Obeng</title>
 <link href="http://adamobeng.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://adamobeng.com/"/>
 <updated>2011-10-07T14:31:59+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://adamobeng.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Adam Obeng</name>
   <email>contact@adamobeng.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Truth and persuasion</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengtruth-and-persuasion"/>
   <updated>2011-09-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./truth-and-persuasion</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Han-teng Liao&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href='http://people.oii.ox.ac.uk/hanteng/2011/09/27/ways-of-seeing-data/'&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; got me thinking about&lt;sup id='fnref:1'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; data visualization as a tool for communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I thought I should take issue with the quote he gives from &lt;a href='http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2011/09/data-visualization-vs-propaganda.html?cid=6a010534b1db25970b015435abb804970c'&gt;David Smith&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;good charts merely present data, and leave the analysis (obvious though it may be) to the viewer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, it seems that a charts which &amp;#8220;merely present data&amp;#8221; are just not possible. The designer of the chart needs to make all sorts of descisions: the order of the data, importance of axes, labels, colours and so on. Few of these are without consequence to the interpretation of the graph, and the futher the chart is from a simple &lt;a href='http://junkcharts.typepad.com/junk_charts/table/'&gt;table&lt;/a&gt;, the greater the potential for bias (or, more charitably &amp;#8216;interpretation&amp;#8217;) there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say &amp;#8216;potential&amp;#8217;, because not every opportunity for bias need be taken. Having said that, not all bias is intentional either. Some of it might be just accidental, or plain &lt;a href='http://junkcharts.typepad.com/junk_charts/2011/06/another-reminder-most-pie-charts-are-unreadable.html'&gt;confusing&lt;/a&gt;. But &lt;a href='http://www.infovis-wiki.net/index.php/Data-Ink_Ratio'&gt;each additional line&lt;/a&gt; on the graph has the potential to introduce spurious anaysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I would venture so far as to say that this is a problem even for the simpler charts that Nathan Yau &lt;a href='http://flowingdata.com/2011/09/23/5-misconceptions-about-visualization/'&gt;advocates&lt;/a&gt; via (&lt;a href='http://smartdatacollective.com/davidmsmith/40688/data-visualization-doesnt-need-be-biased'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2011/09/data-visualization-vs-propaganda.html'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) which are used to convey rational argument without appeals to emotion. There is still ample opportuinity to mislead others (and onesself) by unintentionally misusing a graphic. Indeed, the impression that a graphic is unbiased because it is simple might make us let our guard down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s perhaps unfair to assimilate the use of perceptual tricks to appeals to &lt;em&gt;pathos&lt;/em&gt;: such techniques could be used in rational arguments too. But they are subtle and easy to get wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the fundamental reason for this potential to mislead is also what makes data visualizations useful in the first place: we are phenomenal pattern-matching machines, and we&amp;#8217;re particularly good at visual patterns. We would struggle to interpret 5 million rows of a database, but can easily identify trends when the same data are presented in a different format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='footnotes'&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id='fn:1'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how I start all my blog posts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Offline, but not off the hook</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengoffline-but-not-off-the-hook"/>
   <updated>2011-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./offline-but-not-off-the-hook</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Previously, I &lt;a href='http://adamobeng.com/real-names/'&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; whether Google really cares about real names on Google Plus. In summary, they have little reason to.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='youre_online_offline'&gt;You&amp;#8217;re &amp;#8216;online&amp;#8217; offline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his &lt;a href='http://socialmediacollective.org/2011/08/08/real-name-sites-are-necessarily-inadequate-for-free-speech/'&gt;recent post about the &amp;#8216;nymwars&amp;#8217;&lt;/a&gt; Bernie Hogan also provides some interesting comments on what it means to be &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217; is defined negatively, by opposition to being online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I’ll say that even more strongly – &lt;em&gt;if your speech is not confined to the context you are in – but available to a potentially unknowable audience – you are online.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span&gt;emphasis in original&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re online if what you do and say is &amp;#8220;available to a potentially unknowable audience&amp;#8221;, specifically an audience which you don&amp;#8217;t select, and to which you can&amp;#8217;t adapt your actions&lt;sup id='fnref:1'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time when you&amp;#8217;re online it&amp;#8217;s because your actions are being recorded electronically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you are online when your actions are being digitized and networked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#8217;t have to be carrying out any sort of online activity yourself; if you&amp;#8217;re at a party and someone uploads a photo of you to Facebook, you&amp;#8217;re &amp;#8216;online&amp;#8217;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='youre_online_all_the_time'&gt;You&amp;#8217;re online all the time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this definition of being &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217; is a bit strong. If Bernie&amp;#8217;s right then you&amp;#8217;re always online, unless you&amp;#8217;re not talking to anyone at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, your actions &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; being recorded when you&amp;#8217;re interacting in the real world: they&amp;#8217;re being recorded by the person you&amp;#8217;re talking to. And while they&amp;#8217;re not being &amp;#8220;digitized&amp;#8221;, they are being &amp;#8220;networked&amp;#8221;, passed on through word of mouth, or even encoded at a later time by your interlocutor. And this &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8220;by default&amp;#8221;: unless you make it clear that a conversation is not to be shared&lt;sup id='fnref:2'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, then you can expect it to be shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am engaging in a trust relationship with the curator, but I am not free to say what I want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the real world, everyone that you converse with (bar perhaps medical and legal professionals), is a potential &amp;#8220;curator&amp;#8221;. They can, if they choose, relay your words to others. Of course, you trust them not to do so. And if they were to tell others, there would be no way of proving what you said in private and in confidence &lt;a href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2010/apr/28/gordon-brown-bigoted-woman'&gt;most of the time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, unless you&amp;#8217;re in the middle of the desert, beyond the range of spy satellites and laser microphones, what you say is &amp;#8220;available to a potentially unknowable audience&amp;#8221;. That&amp;#8217;s not a particularly useful definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more workable definition of &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217; might look like what Bernie says just afterwards:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online is on-the-record. Offline is off-the-record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under this definition, it&amp;#8217;s clear that a real-world conversation can be either online or offline, because it can be either on- or off- the record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this binary&lt;sup id='fnref:3'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:3' rel='footnote'&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; definition still isn&amp;#8217;t sufficient. There is still a difference between the online-ness of the real world and that of social networks. I would say that the real world is inherently more offline, because accessing information about your past actions is difficult. It&amp;#8217;s not surprising that a technology designed for information retrieval should make it easy to find things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, being online is a question of degree. You are totally offline if there&amp;#8217;s no &amp;#8216;record&amp;#8217;, or if the &amp;#8216;record&amp;#8217; is impossible to access. &lt;em&gt;The more concrete and available the &amp;#8216;record&amp;#8217; of your actions, the more online you are.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whether the record is accessible is key: even if you&amp;#8217;re recorded, but the record can&amp;#8217;t be transmitted to others, then you can&amp;#8217;t be &amp;#8216;networked&amp;#8217;, so you&amp;#8217;re not meaningfully online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='deniable_networking'&gt;Deniable networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So whether you&amp;#8217;re online is independent of what medium you&amp;#8217;re in: real world or Internet. In fact, there are some forms of electronic communication that are &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217; by default: email, instant messages, and the like. Unlike social networking services, the content of your actions are not published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it should be possible to &lt;em&gt;intentionally&lt;/em&gt; design a social network which had the &amp;#8216;offline&amp;#8217; quality of the real world. We could even give it a cute acronym, like &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;eputationally &lt;em&gt;U&lt;/em&gt;ntraceable &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt;edium &lt;em&gt;O&lt;/em&gt;ffline &lt;em&gt;R&lt;/em&gt;elay, or &lt;em&gt;G&lt;/em&gt;lobally &lt;em&gt;O&lt;/em&gt;ffline &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;ocial &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt;pace over &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt;nternet &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;rotocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what would GOSSIP look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be sensible to base it around something like &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Off_the_record_messaging'&gt;Off-the-Record messaging&lt;/a&gt;. Communications sent via OTR are encrypted and authenticated, so you know who you&amp;#8217;re talking to while the conversation takes place, and no-one can eavesdrop. But the protocol also offers &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deniable_authentication'&gt;deniable authentication&lt;/a&gt;: after the conversation, it cannot be proved who said what. Your &amp;#8216;friends&amp;#8217; are still able to tell others that you said something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like in the real world, however, they can&amp;#8217;t prove it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='footnotes'&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id='fn:1'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to adapt your actions is important so that your actions are context-sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:2'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it could be implicit in the conversational context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:3'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No pun intended, etc, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:3' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>It's not about real names</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengreal-names"/>
   <updated>2011-08-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./real-names</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Google doesn&amp;#8217;t care about real names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve been even vaguely following the controversy about &lt;a href='http://www.google.com/+/demo/'&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ll give you a moment to wipe the coffee off your monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://socialmediacollective.org/2011/08/08/real-name-sites-are-necessarily-inadequate-for-free-speech/'&gt;Bernie Hogan&amp;#8217;s post&lt;/a&gt; is the latest &lt;span style='text-decoration: line-through;'&gt;free publicity for Google+&lt;/span&gt; salvo in the &amp;#8220;nymwars&amp;#8221;: the blogosphere&amp;#8217;s consternation over Google+&amp;#8217;s policy of requiring users to use their real names. Now, although I don&amp;#8217;t have a horse in this race&lt;sup id='fnref:1'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:1' rel='footnote'&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I&amp;#8217;d like to contribute what I think is really going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Bernie, real names in online interaction are sometimes better than pseudonymity. I think this is actually vanishingly rare. Google must realise this, and from the statements they&amp;#8217;ve made, it looks like they do.&lt;sup id='fnref:2'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:2' rel='footnote'&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can only guess at what Google really wants, but if we take them at their word, their goal doesn&amp;#8217;t require real names. The real-names policy on Google+ is just a beta feature, an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://adamobeng.com/what-it-means-to-be-offline'&gt;Next time&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ll also have something to say about what it means to be &amp;#8220;offline&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='real_names_good'&gt;Real names good&amp;#8230;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bernie says that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real names and third-party curation &lt;span&gt;&amp;#8230;&lt;/span&gt; offer many advantages, but freedom is not one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understandably, he doesn&amp;#8217;t go into much detail as to what these advantages might be. But it&amp;#8217;s an interesting question: if we&amp;#8217;re trading freedom for something else, we&amp;#8217;d better make sure it&amp;#8217;s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do we gain from real names? There&amp;#8217;s no single answer, because many different activities are carried out online. Still, I suspect that what Bernie has in mind are activities based on reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion so far has focused on social networks, and as both Bernie and Danah Boyd note (, a person&amp;#8217;s online activities in a social network can belong to different contexts. But as well as targeting different groups of people, what we do online can serve diverse purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take, for instance, the activity in which I am now engaged: debate. Written debate is an activity that also occurs in the real world, perhaps most visibly in the printed media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A newspaper letters page might also have a policy of only allowing real names. There, the policy makes the contributors show that they intend to back up their claims with their real-world reputation. In some cases, it could also reassure the readers with an &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argument_from_authority'&gt;argument from authority&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ideal debate, what people say would stand independently of their reputation, and each statement be judged &lt;a href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/logic-informal/#One'&gt;on its own merits&lt;/a&gt;. But, as Kanye West might say, &amp;#8220;How he stay rational in a room full of trolls?&amp;#8221; People who are acting in bad faith might not be worth debating with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of debate, there are some obvious cases in which you want to know who you&amp;#8217;re talking to: financial transactions, getting real-world advice you need to trust. You might want to use the Web to gather reliable information. In this case, you want to check that your correspondent is who they say they are: journalist, corporate spokesperson, or government minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these reputation-based activities could be carried out on social networking sites with a real-names policy. In fact, real-name sites are not &amp;#8220;necessarily inadequate&amp;#8221; for this sort of interaction, they&amp;#8217;re kinda handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='pseudonyms_better'&gt;&amp;#8230;pseudonyms better?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even offline, there are situations where speaking anonymously is the norm. You might get reliable information from &amp;#8220;a senior politician&amp;#8221;, without knowing who they are (yes, you do generally know who the journalist reporting it is). Monetary transactions are carried out anonymously or pseudonymously (when was the last time Starbucks asked you for ID?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debates held under the Chatham House Rule are another example: participants are forbidden from reporting who spoke or took part. The reasons here are to preserve the freedom of the participants: to allow them to say what they really think without consequence. Such debates aren&amp;#8217;t anonymous by default, like buying a cup of coffee. They&amp;#8217;re anonymous by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there are both online activities which benefit from real names, and offline equivalents of those activities that have various levels of anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;#8217;s no reason why reputation needs to be linked to the real world. In most cases &amp;#8211; especially where anonymity would be OK if you were offline &amp;#8211; it&amp;#8217;s just as good to have a purely online reputation, the reputation attached to a pseudonym (cf. &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ender%27s_Game#Plot_summary'&gt;Locke and Demosthenes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, many people in the offline world interact entirely pseudonymously, but maintain a reputation: does it really matter who Banksy &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; is? Does it even make sense to ask?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to answer the question posed above: it looks like real names only &amp;#8220;offer many advantages&amp;#8221; in the online world when the activity itself benefits from being linked to some offline existence. &lt;em&gt;Real names are a hack: they splice offline mechanisms of trust into the online world&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When exactly does offline reputation matter? It&amp;#8217;s not just that only &amp;#8220;some lucky people give talks to large audiences, they get on the radio or tv&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id='fnref:3'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:3' rel='footnote'&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Only some lucky people are &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Notability'&gt;notable&lt;/a&gt; enough for their real names to matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='real_names_dont_matter'&gt;Real names don&amp;#8217;t matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it looks like Google has realised this. Robert Scoble reports that &lt;a href='https://plus.google.com/107117483540235115863/about'&gt;Vic Gundotra&lt;/a&gt; said that the real-names policy was supposed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;make sure a positive tone gets set here &lt;span&gt;&amp;#8230;&lt;/span&gt; mostly to have a nicer, more personal, community,&lt;sup id='fnref:4'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:4' rel='footnote'&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to require real names if you&amp;#8217;re trying to deter trolls. But it&amp;#8217;s not necessary to use real names to build a community. In fact,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it isn&amp;#8217;t about real names &lt;span&gt;&amp;#8230;&lt;/span&gt; it is about having common names and removing people who spell their names in weird ways, like using upside-down characters, or who are using obviously fake names&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if people have &amp;#8220;common names&amp;#8221;&lt;sup id='fnref:5'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:5' rel='footnote'&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, that they can&amp;#8217;t just shed like a skin, then they carry their reputation with them. People will be &amp;#8220;nice&amp;#8221;, because they don&amp;#8217;t want to get a reputation for being nasty. You can argue that point, but if it&amp;#8217;s true, it&amp;#8217;s a good reason for requiring &amp;#8220;common&amp;#8221;, or consistent names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is still speculative, but Google&amp;#8217;s aim doesn&amp;#8217;t seem to be banning pseudonyms, but rather to enforce their consistency. And that&amp;#8217;s not in order to link what people say online to who they really are, but to make sure they&amp;#8217;re civil. The statement about weird characters&lt;sup id='fnref:6'&gt;&lt;a href='#fn:6' rel='footnote'&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; seems to reinforce this: it&amp;#8217;s about image, the way the network appears to the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that&amp;#8217;s true, real names, like non-&amp;#8220;weird&amp;#8221; names, are being used as a proxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What you are known as&lt;/strong&gt; is not important. &lt;strong&gt;That you are known&lt;/strong&gt; is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://adamobeng.com/what-it-means-to-be-offline'&gt;Next time&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#8217;ll talk about what it really means to be &amp;#8220;offline&amp;#8221;, and whether we can design a online social network that lets you be offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='footnotes'&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id='fn:1'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not on Google+ &lt;a href='http://wellsb.com/post/7022247022/google-plus-for-google-apps-in-the-coming-months'&gt;because I&amp;#8217;ve got a Google Apps account&amp;#8230;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:1' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:2'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this article I will be assuming that Google is, in fact, not evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:2' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:3'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://socialmediacollective.org/2011/08/08/real-name-sites-are-necessarily-inadequate-for-free-speech/'&gt;Real name sites are necessarily inadequate for free speech, by Bernie Hogan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:3' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:4'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://plus.google.com/111091089527727420853/posts/Fddn6rV8mBX'&gt;source: Robert Scoble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:4' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:5'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assume that &amp;#8220;common&amp;#8221; is meant in the sense of &amp;#8216;consistent&amp;#8217;, rather than &amp;#8216;usual&amp;#8217;. Please correct me if I&amp;#8217;m wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:5' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id='fn:6'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some places, people can legally spell their names &amp;#8220;in weird ways&amp;#8221;, or have names that are &amp;#8220;obviously fake&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href='#fnref:6' rev='footnote'&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>EPUB3 Multimedia Features, A Lighting Overview</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengdhox"/>
   <updated>2011-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./dhox</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;a href='http://digital.humanities.ox.ac.uk/DHSS2011/'&gt;Digital Humanities@Oxford Summer School 2011&lt;/a&gt; last week, I was invited to talk briefly about the multimedia features available in EPUB3. Not one to pass up an opportunity for public speaking, I quickly assented. The fact that the Summer School is organized in part by &lt;a href='http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/'&gt;Oxford University Computing Services&lt;/a&gt; might have had something to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that &lt;a href='http://twitter.com/#!/rahtz'&gt;Sebastian &amp;#8216;The Master&amp;#8217; Rahtz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/jamescummings'&gt;James &amp;#8216;Hwæt!&amp;#8217; Cummings&lt;/a&gt; were presenters of this session certainly did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a href='http://digital.humanities.ox.ac.uk/DHSS2011/sessions.html#TEIfacs'&gt;session&lt;/a&gt; on using &lt;a href='http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/index.xml'&gt;TEI&lt;/a&gt; to link text and facsimilies, I talked about a possible end product of the process: a multimedia, interactive EPUB3 eBook. Of course, such an eBook can be used for much more than linking text and facscimiles. In fact, the demo book contained side-by-side manuscript and transcript, embedded video, audio narration synchronised to the text and Javascript-controlled switching between multiple versions of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book, which uses the first page of Beowulf as an used in the demonstration is available &lt;a href='http://adamobeng.com/dhox/beowulf.epub'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This is a slightly different version than that used for the demonstration, using jQuery rather than just Javascript for some interactive functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slides from my presentation are available &lt;a href='http://adamobeng.com/dhox/slides'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#8217;t been involved in the digital humanities before, but judging from the reaction to the demonstration, a little technology can go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The DBO model in HTML5 Canvas and Javascript</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengdbo-model-in-canvas"/>
   <updated>2011-05-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./dbo-model-in-canvas</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve had a little bit of &lt;a href='../analytical-sociology-thesis/'&gt;experience&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agent-based_model'&gt;agent-based modelling&lt;/a&gt;, and so far, I&amp;#8217;ve stumbled across some interesting results. But statistical summaries of models are one thing, while actually having a feel for how a model works is another. These models are inherently dynamic, so there will necessarily be something lost from static pictures of the model, even from graphs of statistics over time. Moreover, ABMs are part of a very quantitative branch of sociology, so it might even be refreshing to reintroduce a little bit of qualitative information (and who doesn&amp;#8217;t like &lt;a href='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blinkenlights'&gt;blinkenlights&lt;/a&gt;?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here&amp;#8217;s one of the graphs I used in my thesis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src='/DBO_example_graph.png' alt='A graph showing the relation between the initial proportion of desires and beliefs and the eventual proportion of desires and beliefs in a basic version of the DBO model' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that&amp;#8217;s a good summary of what&amp;#8217;s going on in the model, don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong. You can see a nice relationship between the parameters. Obviously, graphs like these are essential for summarising information, and you couldn&amp;#8217;t infer this from interacting with the simulation directly. Indeed, in some cases, interacting with the simulation will not even be possible (like when there are too many agents to display comfortably).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, you couldn&amp;#8217;t really have a dynamic, interactive presentation of the model on paper (or even in a PDF). But on the web at least, with a little bit of HTML5 (in particular the &lt;a href='https://developer.mozilla.org/en/Canvas_tutorial'&gt;Canvas&lt;/a&gt; element) you can produce this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script src='../dbo-minified.js' type='text/javascript' /&gt;&lt;body onload='draw();' /&gt;&lt;canvas id='canvas' height='400' width='400' style='margin: 2em;' /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the nodes to change their DBO state; &lt;font color='#0000FF'&gt;blue&lt;/font&gt; nodes have desire, &lt;font color='#FF0000'&gt;red&lt;/font&gt; nodes have belief and &lt;font color='#FF00FF'&gt;purple&lt;/font&gt; nodes have both. The &amp;#8216;step&amp;#8217; button advances the simulation by one step, and the &amp;#8216;reset&amp;#8217; button randomly assigns DBO states to all of the nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you may notice this is a simulation of the DBO model with a fixed set of parameters (in particular, opportunity is being ignored). As such, the behaviour exhibited is pretty limited. This is also for the time being &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; alpha-quality code. Still, it shouldn&amp;#8217;t take too long to get a worthwhile implementation of the DBO model and its variants up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows, I might even expand it to cover some other sociologically-interesting ABMs. &lt;a href='https://secure.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/wiki/Sugarscape'&gt;Sugarscape&lt;/a&gt; in Javascript, anyone?&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Talk at 27C3 -- The Political Philosophy of the Internet</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengtalk-at-CCC"/>
   <updated>2010-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./talk-at-CCC</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1 id='tor_is_peace_software_freedom_is_slavery_wikipedia_is_truth_the_political_philosophy_of_the_internet'&gt;Tor is Peace, Software Freedom is Slavery, Wikipedia is Truth: The Political Philosophy of the Internet&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On something of a whim, I proposed a lecture topic to the &lt;a href='http://events.ccc.de/congress/2010/wiki/Welcome'&gt;27th Chaos Communication Congress&lt;/a&gt;. Somewhat to my surprise, it was accepted. This is the result; an attempt to apply the some of the concepts of political philosophy &amp;#8211; learnt as an undergraduate &amp;#8211; to some questions in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s also a presentation by non-experts to non-experts, so political philosophers should take it with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='abstract'&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet began as state-sponsored anarchy, but it is now the tool of first resort for dissidents and propagandists alike. The poster-child project of the Free Software Movement runs on the authority of a single person; the rest clash over the very definition of the word &amp;#8216;free&amp;#8217;. A company which pictured itself as smashing Big Brother is now perceived as one of the most secretive and authoritarian in the industry; and for another, &amp;#8216;Don&amp;#8217;t Be Evil&amp;#8217; is proving to be a challenging motto to live by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk aims to present a view of the societies of Internet from the perspective of political philosophy. &lt;em&gt;Political philosophy is not politics&lt;/em&gt;, in the same way that computer science is not programming. It&amp;#8217;s not the politics about the Internet, but the politics &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; the Internet. Even so, events at any particular place or time just provide examples to be studied. Political philosophy is meta-politics, it&amp;#8217;s about the trends in politics and the theories we use to understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real-world political systems have striking parallels in the evolution of the Internet: there was primitive anarchy before Eternal September, the era of walled gardens resembled that of Ancient Greek city-states, which were succeeded by more-or-less liberal regimes following the geographical territories of real-world governments. Because of its rapid evolution, mass participation, and highly complex human interaction, the Internet should be subjected to the sorts of questions that political philosophers ask. On the Internet, what is freedom? Do we have obligations to those in control? To each other? What rights do we have? What can we own?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we know the way it is, we can ask how it should be&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='downloads_now_available'&gt;Downloads (now available)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='../download/slides.pdf'&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='../download/printslides.pdf'&gt;Printable Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='../download/lecture.pdf'&gt;Lecture text&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id='video'&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video of the talk is available on &lt;a href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tXCV_z_M0RA'&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href='http://mirror.fem-net.de/CCC/27C3/'&gt;the CCC website&lt;/a&gt;, and on &lt;a href='mailto:contact@adamobeng.com'&gt;request&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Arduino syntax file for vim</title>
   <link href="http://adamobengarduino-vim-syntax-file"/>
   <updated>2010-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./arduino-vim-syntax-file</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;#8217;ve been tinkering with electronics hardware. Let me tell you, for someone who&amp;#8217;s more comfortable with software, the experience can be quite scary: if you mess up your code, the worst that happens is that it fails to compile, or maybe the interpreter spits out an error. But this electronics stuff is &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt;! If you do something wrong it could literally blow up in your face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, for people like me, there&amp;#8217;s the &lt;a href='http://www.arduino.cc/'&gt;Arduino&lt;/a&gt; project to hold your (badly scorched) hand. Doubly-fortunately, you can still use &lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/'&gt;your favourite powerful text editor&lt;/a&gt; to do so. To get syntax-highlighting working in vim for Arduino&amp;#8217;s .pde, you have to install &lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=2654'&gt;a script&lt;/a&gt; written by Johannes Hoff. The Arduino project is constantly changing, so I updated the syntax file to add some new features (notably some stuff relating to the Arduino Mega).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The updated version is now available on &lt;a href='http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=2654'&gt;vim.org&lt;/a&gt;. Hopefully it will prevent some explosions (or, more likely, bricked microcontrollers).&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Undergraduate Thesis in Analytical Sociology</title>
   <link href="http://adamobenganalytical-sociology-thesis"/>
   <updated>2010-04-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://adamobeng.com./analytical-sociology-thesis</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update:&lt;/em&gt; An interactive version of the central model of my thesis is now &lt;a href='/dbo-model-in-canvas/'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id='small_worlds_sour_grapes_and_social_deprivation_the_computational_application_of_peter_hedstrms_dbo_theory'&gt;Small Worlds, Sour Grapes and Social Deprivation: the Computational Application of Peter Hedström&amp;#8217;s DBO Theory&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id='research_proposal'&gt;Research proposal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href='http://www.cambridge.org/asia/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780511133312&amp;amp;ss=exc'&gt;Dissecting the Social&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='http://www.nuffield.ox.ac.uk/General/Members/hedstrom.aspx'&gt;Peter Hedström&lt;/a&gt; proposes an agent-based sociological theory in which each individual&amp;#8217;s action is determined by their desires, beliefs and opportunities. He then uses this model to simulate social interaction, and reaches certain conclusions about the macro-social consequences of different forms of agency. While the DBO theory itself is psychologically compelling, the parameters of the model that are used to apply it are very restricted. By varying the assumptions made in the practical application of the theory, I hope to gain more insight into the predictive possibilities and theoretical implications of this agent-based model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='description'&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this undergraduate thesis as part of my BA in Philosophy, Politics and Economics at the University of Oxford, under the supervision of &lt;a href='http://www.nuffield.ox.ac.uk/General/Members/hedstrom.aspx'&gt;Peter Hedström&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main parameters that I varied were the nature of individual decision-making mechanisms and the types of networks on which agents interact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulations were run using a number of Python scripts using the &lt;a href='https://code.google.com/p/python-graph/'&gt;python-graph&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='https://code.google.com/p/pydot/'&gt;pydot&lt;/a&gt; libraries, outputting to &lt;a href='http://graphviz.org/'&gt;GraphViz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://www.gnuplot.info/'&gt;GnuPlot&lt;/a&gt;. For what it&amp;#8217;s worth, the scripts written for these simulations come to 4,284 Source Lines Of Code (a statistic generated using David A. Wheeler&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8217;&lt;a href='http://www.dwheeler.com/sloccount/'&gt;SLOCCount&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8217;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis won the &lt;a href='http://www.ox.ac.uk/feesandfunding/ugcurrent/other/prizes/gibbs/'&gt;Gibbs Thesis prize in Politics&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id='downloads'&gt;Downloads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thesis is not yet available for download, but may be soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
